A Guide to the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS) Institutional Self-Study Records, 1961-1992: UA 0043
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS) Institutional Self-Study Records,
1961-1992
Special Collections, James Madison University
Madison College
James Madison University
UA 0043
.66 cubic feet; 2 boxes
The SACS Institutional Self-Study Records contain documents related to James Madison University's accreditation process, administered by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, from 1961-1992.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Self-Study Reports from 1961 and 1981 were present in the cage at the time of founding.
Separated Materials
In 2018, five Affirmative Action reports were transferred to UA 0005, Office of Affirmative Action Records, 1977-1988, and four Academic Program Review documents were transferred to UA 0002, Academic Affairs: Academic Program Reviews (APR), 1976-present (bulk 1992-present).
Administrative History
The Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS), now the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools and School Commission on Colleges (SACSCOC), is a regional accreditation agency for degree-granting higher education institutions. JMU was issued its first "institutional report card" by SACS in 1927, and continues to require SACSCOC accreditation in order to award baccalaureate, masters and doctorate degrees. SACSCOC requires that academic institutions renew or reaffirm their accreditation every ten years. As part of the reaffirmation process, JMU undertakes a comprehensive self-study that demonstrates that the university is in compliance with the SACSCOC criteria for accreditation, evaluates all aspects of the university, and recommends a future course of action. The university submits a "Fifth Year Interim Report" in between self-study reports.
Scope and Content
The SACS Institutional Self-Study Records contain documents related to the accreditation process administered by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, from 1961-1992. Topics of the self-study evaluation include educational programs, faculty and educational support services, administrative processes, financial resources, and institutional policies, among other topics.
The majority of the reports were prepared for the 1961 Self-Study, submitted during the tenure of President G. Tyler Miller. The 1961 departmental and committee reports cover topics such as university and departmental objectives, faculty and staff listings, details of the facilities and departmental resources, course offerings, and program evaluations. These reports form the basis of the final report, the "Summary Report of the Self-Evaluation Study, 1961" (1:1), submitted to the SACS evaluating body. The collection also contains SACS manuals and responses to recommendations made to by the SACS reaffirmation committee.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged chronologically and alphabetically.
Related Materials
The finalized SACS Institutional Self-Study Reports from 1961 – 2002 are bound and available in Special Collections.
Bibliography
"James Madison University SACSCOC Accreditation." James Madison University. http://www.jmu.edu/sacscoc/. (Accessed May 7, 2018).
"Southern Association of Colleges and Schools and School Commission on Colleges." http://www.sacscoc.org/. (Accessed May 7, 2018).
Index Terms
Subjects:
James Madison University; Madison College; Education, Higher -- Evaluation; Education, Higher -- United States -- Planning; Universities and colleges -- Evaluation; Universities and colleges -- Planning
Genre and Form Terms:
Administrative reports; Handbooks and manuals; Questionnaires
- Summary Report of the Self-Evaluation Study, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Committee Report: Educational Program of Madison College, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Committee Report: Faculty, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Committee Report: Finance and the Utilization of our Physical Plant, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Committee Report: Library, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Committee Report: Organization, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Committee Report: Purposes, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Committee Report: Special Activities, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Committee Report: Student Personnel, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Department Report: Art, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Department Report: Biology, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Department Report: Business and Business Education, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Department Report: Chemistry, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Department Report: Education and Psychology, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Department Report: English Language, Literature and Speech, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Department Report: Foreign Languages, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Department Report: Geology, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Department Report: Graduate Program, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Department Report: Health and Physical Education, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Department Report: Home Economics, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Department Report: Library Science, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Department Report: Mathematics, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Department Report: Music, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Department Report: Physics, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Department Report: Social Science and History, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Southern Association of Colleges Self-Evaluation Manual, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- SACS Institutional Self-Study Manual, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- College and Departmental Summaries, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- SACS: Report of the Reaffirmation Committee, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Responses to the Recommendation of the SACS Reaffirmation Committee, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)